This video is sponsored by Card Kingdom.
If you want Magic singles or sealed
product, use my link in the description.
Hi everyone, I'm Neon and with this
video I'm kicking off my Reality
Fracture set review. This is a good
place to begin because these videos help
introduce the major synergies for each
color pair in the set. And also,
multicolored cards often tend to be some
of the coolest, most powerful cards in a
set. For each of these cards, I'll
discuss how I think they'll perform in
limited, that means draft and sealed.
And I'll punctuate each evaluation with
a letter grade. If you're new to my set
reviews and unsure of what my letter
grades mean, you can find a guide in the
description. There are a few important
things to keep in mind as I review these
cards. first because we're only talking
about draft and sealed. I'm only going
to be talking about cards that can be
found in play boosters. In other words,
cards with the FRA code in the lower
lefthand corner. If you think a card is
missing from this video, it's probably
one of the commander cards which have F
FRC in the lower lefthand corner. These
are also my evaluations of these cards
before it's possible to play this new
limited format because my goal is to
have my set review done in time for the
pre-release and that means I'll be wrong
about some stuff. But as the format
comes into focus, I'll do videos
discussing how things have panned out.
Lastly, I want to let you know that
there are some set review related perks
for being a channel member or a patron.
You get access to my ongoing set notes
during preview season, which is kind of
like a rough draft of this set review.
And you'll also get a spreadsheet with
all of my grades once the set review is
complete. If those perks interest you,
check out the description where you can
find out how to support the channel
using one of those methods. All right,
without further ado, let's take a look
at the multicolored and colorless cards
in Reality Fracture. The set has one
colorless non-artifact and that'll be
what kicks us off. Emer the exigent
doom. It's 10 generic mana for a 1212
legendary aldrazi at mythic rare. When
you cast it, you untap all your lands.
It has flying and trample. It has ward
sacrifice three permanence. And you can
pay three generic and exile it from your
hand and target land gets tap for two
colorless until this card is cast from
exile. And you may cast this card for as
long as it remains exiled. In limited,
this will often feel like a glorified
mana rock, and that's not all that
exciting in your typical format. It's
cool that in the late game, it can come
down as a big scary creature, and the
mana it gives you can help you get
there, but it's also true that by that
point, the ward isn't really going to
make it that much harder for your
opponent to kill your creature. And
that's not really what I want to hear
about a card that costs this much mana.
Untapping all of your lands also not
something that matters in a big way in
the extreme late game, which is when
this is going to come down. I do like
that it does something early and ramps
your mana and there are going to be some
decks maybe in red green which is the
rampiest color pair in the format that
can use this be happy with the ramp and
then cast this late but I think it's
going to be a little bit too slow to be
that viable and the fact that it doesn't
really add to the board until you
actually cast it is a pretty big
problem. I think it's just to see. All
right, let's move into multicolored
cards now. Starting with Arid Constrari
for one generic a red and two green.
It's a five four legendary elder sphinx
at mythic rare. It's got flying and when
it enters or dies, you create a
heartwood token. That's a red and green
artifact with tap add red or green and
you can pay six generic to create
another heartwood token and then ergoni
gets plus x plus zero until end of turn
where x is a number of artifacts you
control. A four mana 54 flyer that just
spit out one of these mana rocks would
be an incredible card. It's true that
you don't always need heartwood tokens,
but they are real value especially in a
color pair that cares about artifacts
and ramping mana. And that's what red
green is, as this guy is showing us.
Basically, he's a creature that can just
win the game with raw stats and its
activated ability. And if it doesn't do
that, it leaves behind some very real
value. That's pretty much the definition
of a bomb, giving it an A. Next up, it's
Avatar of Burgeoning Echoes, which for a
green and a blue is a two three avatar
at mythic rare, and it has landfall,
meaning whenever your land you control
enters, something happens. In this case,
you empower Jace 2. This is the
headliner mechanic in the format. And
empower Jace 2 means put two loyalty
counters on a Jace token you control. If
you don't control one, first create a
blue J planaineswalker token with minus
one surveill one and minus three draw a
card. On top of that, the avatar also
says planes walkers you control have
minus 10. Put a plus one plus one
counter and target creature for each
land you control. So empower is a really
cool mechanic. It inherently gives you
value in the form of a plains walker.
And that planaineswalker can straight up
draw you cards if you have enough
counters on him and he can surveil when
he doesn't. There are various payoffs in
the set like Avatar of Burgeoning Echos
for having a planaineswalker around. And
if you are landfalling, like you play
this on turn two and you landfall every
turn, there's a pretty decent chance
Jace does end up with a bunch of loyalty
and might actually put a bunch of
counters on something. But I think most
of this card's value simply comes from
the fact that it's going to keep making
sure you have a Jace around. You're
going to be drawing cards. you're going
to be surveilling. And then it has
pretty good stats, too. Just seems like
a nice value engine. I'm giving it a B+.
Next up, it's Blessed Ghoul, which for a
black white hybrid mana is a one- one
zombie cleric at common. It's got
lifelink, and you can pay two generic
and a white black hybrid mana to return
it from your graveyard to your hand.
This is a solid little one drop that
works fine in the format's graveyard
decks. And with Jason's ability to
surveil, throwing this in the graveyard
kind of feels like drawing a card,
albeit a pretty mediocre one. But one
mana one lifelinkers also tend to be
pretty decent in decks that are good at
augmenting creatures and that's what red
white wants to do in the format. So I
think this is a C. Next up it's Bloom
Brute which for two generic a green and
a white is a 44 plant elemental at
uncommon. Whenever you gain life you
draw a card and this ability triggers
only once each turn and you can pay four
generic a green and a white and target
creature gains trample and lifelink
until end of turn. This has a solid
baseline as a four mana 44 and it's a
really great payoff for gaining life
which is exactly what green white wants
to be doing in this format. If you're
flooding out that activated ability plus
the card you draw goes a long way
towards overcoming your problems. I do
wish it did a little something more
upfront, but I think it's pretty good on
the whole. I'm giving it a B minus. Next
up it's Charge the Sanctum which for two
generic and a red white hybrid mana is a
common instant. And it says, "Choose
one. Creatures you control get plus two
plus zero intell or target creature gets
plus2 plus zero and gains first strike
until end of turn. Put a plus and plus
one counter on it." The trumpet blast
mode is good in the exact right spot
when you've gone really wide. However,
that spot doesn't happen often enough in
most formats for this to be a playable
card if that's all it was. Adding the
combat trick mode does change things in
a big way. It's effectively three mana
for plus three plus one in a first
strike and then plus one plus one of
that remains behind. That'll certainly
win a lot of combat. Although three mana
is about two more than I normally feel
great about playing for a combat trick,
especially one that isn't very good
against removal, but the added trumpet
blast mode does make up for things a
little as this can be like a win
condition in the exact right spot and
it's an okay trick when you're not in
that spot. On the whole, I think it's a
C minus. Next up, it's Clash of
Elements, which for one generic, a blue
and a red is an uncommon instant. Says,
"Choose target non-land permanent. Its
owner may put it on top of their
library. If they do, Clash of Elements
deals two damage to them. if they didn't
put the card on top of their library,
they put it on the bottom. This is a
neat take on the kind of spell we see in
pretty much every set to the point that
it's kind of getting old. And what I
mean by that is a card that lets you put
an opposing creature on the top or
bottom of your opponent's library where
they make the choice. Normally, it's
monoled and costs four mana. And
normally, there's not a punishment for
your opponent putting the card on top of
their library instead of on the bottom.
And normally, it can't also target
non-land permanence. It can usually just
target creatures. So, the fact that this
is such a huge upgrade over like a C++
level removal spell that we see in
almost every set is amazing. It's an
upgrade in every single way. It's more
flexible. It's more powerful. It's
cheaper. So, this looks great to me. I'm
giving it a B. And it doesn't hurt that
blue red really likes spells, so you'll
even get more value out of it. Next up,
it's Craft Work Crusher, which for three
generic, two red and two green is a 75
artifact creature bore constructed
uncommon. It's got trample and when it
enters you choose two. This creature
deals four damage to target creature or
planaineswalker. Create a two two
colorless wizard soldier creature token
named cadet or draw a card. So the first
time I read this card, I thought it just
said choose one and I thought it was
already pretty good. The fact that it
says choose two is incredible. The
double red double green is going to be a
little difficult to produce sometimes,
but the format's heartwood tokens, which
red green has a lot of, are likely to
offset that problem a bit. Either way,
this is a really strong card since it
has an interest trigger that will almost
always generate two cards of value. The
removal mode is often the most powerful,
so you'll almost always be choosing
that, but sometimes you need to go wide
or dig for removal for something even
bigger, and this can do those things,
too, in addition to being a very real
card when it gets turned sideways. I
think this uncommon is actually a bomb.
It's going to be easier to cast than it
normally would, and it just has amazing
three for one value, giving it an A
minus. Next up, it's Denzelor Fateold,
who for one generic, a white, and two
blue is a three four legendary elder
sphinx at mythic rare. He's got flash
and flying. Whenever you scry or
surveil, you put a plus and plus one
counter on each creature you control.
Flashing him in to block a smaller
creature can set you up with a two for
one from the get-go. And obviously, this
scrier surveil trigger is very strong.
It's a little sad that it doesn't have a
built-in way to trigger it. Even if it
cost a lot of mana or something, it
would mean that if you brick on your
draw, you'll still get something more
than a four mana 3 four flyer with
flash. Sometimes that's all you'll get,
but this is also cheap enough to
manufacture spots where you can spend
that mana and still scry or surveil. And
empower Jace makes it far more likely
than it would be in most sets that you
can cast densor and surveil immediately,
assuming you have a Jason play with one
loyalty. In the end, I think this ends
up being a bomb, although it does kind
of take a little bit more work than the
other sphinxes in this cycle do. I'm
giving it an A minus. Next up, it's
Desperate Future Scribe, which for two
generic, a white and a blue is a three
four core scout and uncommon. got flying
and at the beginning of combat on your
turn, another target creature you
control gets plus one plus one until end
of turn. If you use Screr surveil this
turn, put a plus and plus one counter on
that creature instead. A four mana 3
four flyer that could only give plus one
plus one to something at the beginning
of combat would be a playable card. And
this has the added bonus of giving you a
counter a not insignificant percentage
of the time. And as we just saw, this
color pair is really into surveilling.
And again, those Jace tokens will make
that easier than it would be in most
formats. Being a combat trigger also
means you get some value right away too,
even if it's not a counter. I think this
is a B minus. Next up, it's emergency
phytomedic, which for a green white
hybrid mana is a one-1 dryad cleric at
common that enters prepared. So, this is
a returning mechanic. And if a creature
is prepared, it has the ability to let
you cast a spell that's also on the
card. And once you do cast that spell,
the creature becomes unprepared. In this
case, the spell is seed suture, which
for a green white hybrid mana is a
sorcery. that puts a plus and plus one
counter in target creature and you gain
a life. We're going to see seed suture a
lot as every card at common or uncommon
that's associated with green white has
this exact same prepared spell. This
looks like a good common. It's like a
better version of the two mana 1 one we
often get that puts a counter somewhere
and that's usually a playable card. One
thing I really like about seed suture is
that it synergizes well with like the
red white deck which really likes plus
and plus one counters and the life gain
deck which is the green white deck. And
both decks are also happy to get the
other effect off of this, too. Is
getting a whole counter for one mana and
gaining a life, helping you with synergy
is all really good, especially on a card
you can run out on turn one or run out
on turn two and put the counter on it or
something else right away. This looks
like a nice common. I'm giving it a C+.
Next up, it's Enrust the Spark, which
for three generic, a green and a blue is
a rare sorcery. You may sacrifice a
Planaineswalker. If you do, search your
library for a Planaineswalker card, put
it on the battlefield, and then shuffle.
This represents like a huge moment in
the story and it's a pretty cool card
for formats other than limited, but it's
kind of a bummer that it's going to be
so bad here. It's pretty much trash and
limited. I get the idea. You could
empower Jace and then sacrifice that
token to surge up your bomb
planaineswalker, but making all of that
lineup and having five mana is just not
going to work nine times out of 10. And
spending five mana for this is more
expensive than most of the
planaineswalkers in the set are anyway.
So, it's not like you're getting a
discount. You're two for oneing yourself
upfront and maybe it's not quite a two
for one if it's a Jace token, but you're
giving something up on board. You're
spending a bunch of mana, doing it at
sorcery speed. And then there's the fact
that most of the time you're not going
to have a planaineswalker in your deck
anyway because they're all mythic rare
in this set unless they are empower
Jace. It's just an F. Next up, it's Fate
Hold Charm. It's a white and a blue for
an uncommon instant. Like all charms, it
gives you three choices. They are draw a
card and power Jace two. Return target
spell or creature to its owner's hand
and creatures you control get plus one
plus two until end of turn. The bounce
mode is always going to feel pretty
nice, especially when you can interact
with the stack. The third mode can help
you win out of nowhere in the right
spot. And the first mode's going to be
reasonable value, too, because you get
to empower Jace and draw a card. That's
not quite a two for one, but it's closer
than you'd think since you only need
three loyalty to draw a card. So, on the
whole, I love that this has a second
mode that is most frequently going to be
useful. But then two other modes that
are great in the right spot, it's a B.
Next up, it's Fate Hold Chronologist,
which for one generic and a blue white
hybrid mana is a one-two flyer at
common. It enters prepared, and the blue
white prepare spell is peer review,
which is two generic and a blue white
hybrid mana, and it makes a two two
colorless wizard soldier creature token
named Cadet, and you surveil one. So
later in the game, this will feel like a
five mana, one two flyer that makes a
two two and surveills one. That's not a
terrible card, and this is, of course,
better since you can run it out in turn
two when you need to, and there are
payoffs for surveilling in this set, as
we've already seen. You can also look at
it as a card that single-handedly fills
your two drop and three drop slots on
your curve, albeit kind of
inefficiently. But one card giving you
two bodies and making sure you can use
your mana two turns in a row is no small
thing. Still, it's hard to go above a C
here. Next up, it's Ferocity of the
Hunt, which for one generic and a black
green hybrid mana is a common
enchantment aura with flash and enchant
creature. Enchanted creature gets plus
and plus hero and has death touch. When
enchanted creature dies, return that
card to the battlefield tapped under its
owner's control. Flashing the sin will
almost always benefit you as the death
touch means your creature can take down
anything. And because your creature
returns to the battlefield, you're
always going to come out ahead in that
exchange. This is especially true if
there is a death trigger or an interest
trigger. It's also useful against most
removal. It's a little bit expensive.
You're not always going to have mana up
for it, but this feels like a trick with
broad enough applications that it'll see
consistent play. giving it a C. Next up,
it's Frostbite Pyrantal, which for one
blue and two red. It's a four- four
elemental at rare, it does trample and
haste, and when it deals combat damage
to a player, you draw two cards. And at
the beginning of the instep, you
sacrifice this creature. This is a fun
blue red version of ball lightning, and
I think it's pretty good on the whole.
It doesn't add to the board permanently.
Trample and haste makes it easy for you
to find a window where it'll slam in for
some damage and draw you two cards. And
that's an exchange I feel pretty good
about. It'll feel kind of like a
divination that does some damage, which
I'm definitely on board with. I'm giving
it a B. Next up, it's Grim Repriser,
which for a black and a red is a two two
zombie bard at uncommon with prowess,
and you can pay a black and a red to
return it from your graveyard to the
battlefield with a finality counter on
it. Activate only if an opponent has
been dealt non-combat damage this turn.
And that non-combat damage thing is the
black red theme in this set. So, black
red is going to be able to do non-combat
damage. So getting two instances of this
grim repriser in a game is fairly doable
and the cost to return it to the
battlefield is reasonable. Also, you can
do it at instant speed and it enters
untapped, both of which aren't things we
see all the time. And I'm glad they did
that because it's already asking you to
do something else to even have access to
the ability in the first place. Still,
it's an underwhelming body on the whole,
and it's not always going to be
automatic to set up either. I think it's
a C+. Next up, it's Ingress Stinger
Quill, which for a black and two red is
a one four legendary elder sphinx at
mythic rare. It's got flying. Whenever a
creature you control attacks, that
creature deals one damage to each
opponent, and you can pay four generic
to make a two two colorless wizard
soldier creature token named cadet. Then
creatures you control gain haste until
it turn. So, this attack trigger will
ping for every single attacking
creature. So, it can contribute
significant damage out of nowhere. And
even if you play this on curve, there's
a good chance you can swing with your
two drop and get that extra value right
away. It also counts itself, and that's
good since its high toughness and flying
makes it reasonably easy to attack with
on mini boards. The token generating
ability is going to be awesome, too.
You're overpaying a little bit for a 22,
but it's repeatable and instant speed,
and it's the kind of thing that in the
late game will just allow you to grind
out a win because you have something to
do with all your mana when you're
flooding out and your opponent doesn't.
You won't always be able to get
immediate value out of this guy, but
it's so cheap that you also aren't going
to get super blown out by removal here.
And if it sticks around, it turns into a
pretty real token factory that pressures
the opponent's life total in a big way.
I think it's an A. Next up, it's
Constari Charm, which for a red and a
green is an uncommon instant. It says,
"Choose one. Constari Charm deals six
damage to target creature with flying.
Put two plus one plus one counters on
target creature gains trample until it
turn three colorless." This is probably
the weakest of this cycle in limited
where the third mode, the ritual mode,
is rarely going to be worth it. You
don't want to go down a card for a one-
turn mana boost. Most of the time you're
basically two for oneing yourself if
that's what you do. And this one is also
colorless, which is super awkward. The
first mode can kill most of the flyers
in the set, which is nice, but super
situational. And the second mode is a
quality combat trick, but not an insane
one. I think this is just a C. Next up,
it's Constari Improviser, which for one
generic and a red green hybrid mana is a
two two human artificer at common. It
enters prepared, and it has the constra,
which is called soul tether. It's too
generic and a red green hybrid mana for
a sorcery that makes a heartwood token.
A two drop that can ramp your mana and
help with artifact synergies is the kind
of two drop you're basically always
playing the first couple of copies of
and red green especially. It's another
card that can fill two points on your
curve, though not quite as effectively
as a card that adds to the board with
both copies because the token doesn't
really add to the board in a significant
way, but it will help your mana on
future turns and help your artifact
synergies. Seems like a quality two
drop. I'm giving it a C+. Next up, it's
Qua Vigor Bloom, which for three
generic, a green, and two white is a 66
legendary elder sphinx at mythic rare.
It's got flying, vigilance, lifelink,
and word two. Whenever you gain life,
you create a colorless artifact token
named Lotus. With tap, sacrifice this
token, add three mana of any one color.
This ability triggers only once each
turn. Just a creature with these
keywords and stats is probably a B at
the very worst. It's true, you don't get
something right away from it, but it's a
body that wres havoc on combat
immediately. The huge lifelinker often
means your opponent no longer has a good
attack since it can just gobble
something up and gain you a ton of life
in the process, not to mention some
mana. Throw in the ward and you have a
creature that generally can't be killed
for a tiny investment. And should you be
allowed to untap, this will quickly put
the game out of reach by slamming in for
six, gaining you six, still being
available to block on your opponent's
turn. There are also going to be spots
where your opponent can spend four or
five to kill this, but that's not a
massive blowout. Also, if you gain life
the turn this comes down, you can still
get a Lotus and it enters untapped, so
it's not unheard of that you can do
something with it right away. You won't
always have a board that can give you a
lotus immediately, and you don't always
have a reason to use Lotus mana, but
this is a creature where it's stat line
plays a huge role in making it
excellent. It's going to be one of the
scariest things you can possibly see on
the board when it comes to combat, and
ward being in the mix helps solidify it
in that spot. And then if you get all
this extra mana out of it too, you're
gonna really be in business giving it an
A. Next up, it's Mind Meanderer, which
for three generica green and two blue is
a four four birdfish illusion at
uncommon. It's got flying. It has
vigilance as long as you control a Jace
planaineswalker. The green blue color
pair really cares about Jace
Plaineswalkers. And when this creature
enters, it fights up to one target
creature an opponent controls. So even
without the Jace planaineswalker upside,
this would be pretty good. It can come
down and kill like a 3- three and then
you have a 44 hanging out and
threatening the opponent. These
creatures who fight when they enter do
have some limitations on what they can
kill since you don't usually want your
creature that's doing the fighting to
die. I mean, you can do that in a pinch
and turn this into a six- mana removal
spell. But that's not nearly as good as
a six- mana 44 flyer that kills your
opponent's three drop is. And we've seen
time and time again that those
limitations still allow this kind of
creature to generate a meaningful two
for one. I think this is a B. Next up,
it's Null Summoner, which for two
generic, a blue and a black, is a 4-2
human warlock at rare. When it enters,
if you cast it, target opponent reveals
their hand. You choose a non-land card
from it, exile that card, and it has
threshold. As long as there are seven or
more cards in your graveyard, you may
cast the exiled card, and mana of any
type can be spent to cast that spell.
This is great. It's a body that can
trade for lots of stuff, and when it
enters, it just blasts the best card out
of your opponent's hand while giving you
a bunch of information.
That alone would be enough for this to
be a B+. That's just a great two for one
up front. And later in the game, if
she's still around, you might also be
able to cast the spell, in which case
you get like a three for one. And blue
black is good at milling itself. We're
going to see that some in this video.
That's what it's the most interested in
doing. So getting threshold online even
by turn four isn't impossible. So the
floor here is that you get a really good
two for one. You disrupt your opponent
in a big way. Completely derail
everything they were planning to do. And
the ceiling is that, oh, by the way, you
also cast whatever the best spell in
their hand was though, you do need to
have your graveyard set up and you do
need some time to do it most of the
time. That's just great value on top of
what's already an excellent card. I
think this is a bomb. Giving it an A.
Next up, it's Paradox Shaper, which for
one generic and a blue black hybrid mana
is a 1- three octopus wizard at
uncommon. At the beginning of your
upkeep, if it isn't prepared, it becomes
prepared. And you can pay two generic to
put target card from your grave on the
bottom of your library. And it has the
blue black prepare spell which is called
omit variables. It's a sorcery for one
blue black hybrid mana that mills three
cards. So this is a card that really
needs you to have graveyard stuff going
on. Otherwise, it doesn't do that much.
The good news is you're going to have a
deck that's doing exactly that pretty
often in blue black and in black green.
In which case this is a powerful enabler
like for the rare we just saw. Also,
having a built-in way to save you from
milling yourself out is irrelevant in
most limited formats. But I think this
is one where it's actually going to come
up sometimes. There are multiple cards
in the set with omit variables after all
and lots of other ways to mill yourself.
And once you reach that point, it's not
only like, hey, this saves me from
killing myself. It's also I get to
decide what card from my graveyard I
draw every single turn. And that's also
pretty powerful. It does take a lot of
synergy. It doesn't do that much on its
own to really get going, but it's going
to be a key card in blue, black, and
probably in black, green, too, giving it
a C++.
Next up, it's Primal Witch Stalker,
which for one generic, a black and a
green, is a two-1 wolf at uncommon. It
has menace, and when it enters, you mill
four cards, and when you do, you return
target land card from your graveyard to
the battlefield tapped. So, black green
is also about milling itself. It's more
interested in having creatures and lands
in the graveyard. And this will
typically give you a nice little two for
one while ramping your mana and helping
you with graveyard synergy. It'll feel
like a very nice play on turn three. And
even in the late game, it can help get
you going. I'm giving it a B minus.
Next, it's Proctor of Potential, which
for a white and a blue is a 3-1 human
cleric at rare. When it or another
creature you control enters, you surveil
one. And you can pay a white blue hybrid
mana to return this card from your
graveyard to the battlefield with a
finality counter on it. Activate only if
you've scried or surveiled this turn.
Even if this was just a two mana three-
one that let me surveil one when it
entered, it would be a playable card.
And even if it only surveiled one when
it or another creature you control
enters, it would be a really good card
obviously, especially in the blue white
color pair. But this gets even better
than all of that because it can come
back from the graveyard. It'll survail
again when it does that, of course, and
then set you up for more surveills in
the future. It's just going to feel
really good on turn two. and it's pretty
much always a relevant card, especially
in the blue white color pair where you
can leverage those surveills into even
more value. I think it's a B+.
Next up, it's Prudent Fates Seir, which
for one generic and two blue white
hybrid mana is an uncommon dwarf wizard.
It's a 1/4. It enters prepared whenever
you scry or surveil. Creatures you
control get plus zero until end of turn.
This ability triggers only once each
turn. It has the blue white prepare
spell, which is pure review. That's the
one that makes a two two colorless
wizard soldier creature token named
cadet and surveills one. This looks
pretty nice. A three mana 14 obviously
isn't great, but this scrier surveil
trigger means business since it buffs
all of your stuff. And the fate sear's
own prepare spell will trigger it while
also giving you a second body. That
means there's a mode where you draw this
late and just spend seven mana for a one
four, a two, a surveil, and plus one
plus zero to your whole board. That's
usually going to be pretty nice at that
stage of the game. And of course, just
being a card that makes two relevant
bodies itself has value. I'm giving this
a B minus.
Next up, it's recursive recruitment,
which for two generic, a blue and a
black is an uncommon sorcery. Create two
two colorless wizard soldier creature
tokens named cadet. If this spell was
cast from a graveyard, you put a plus
and plus one counter on each of them for
every three cards in your graveyard.
There are a few cards that make you do
math with your graveyard, which is sort
of the broader theme of Blue Black in
this set, and this is one of those. So,
four mana for two two twos is solid. And
flashing this back later to get two more
of those tokens, probably with a
significant buff, is great, but eight
mana is a lot, and this is the kind of
card whose fortunes will really depend
on the speed of the format. If you're
getting to eight mana game in and game
out, and you're getting to the point
where you've almost milled yourself out
using the blue black prepare spell guy
who can do it every single turn, then of
course this is going to be really good.
you're going to pay eight and you're
going to get two huge tokens later in
the game, which probably push you over
and get you to the point where you can
just win. But there are lots of formats
where getting to eight mana is
incredibly uncommon and very difficult
to achieve. And if this is one of those,
it's mostly just a four mana card that
makes two twos, which is fine, but it's
not something that you would be
particularly excited about on the whole.
I think it's safe to think that you'll
be able to get to eight mana in this
format a decent chunk of the time, but
not always. That's how most formats are.
And if that's the case, I think it's a
C++. Next up, it's Solarium Sentry,
which for a green and a white is a
three- three cat soldier at rare.
Whenever an opponent casts a spell with
mana value two or less, you gain two
life. Watchwolf with upside is going to
feel pretty good, especially on turn
two. Although, keep in mind when a card
costs two different colors of mana, it
can be harder to cast on turn two as
well, especially in limited. Still,
limited decks tend to have lots of two
drops and especially if you're on the
play with this, there's a good chance
you gain two life on your opponent's
next turn. And a three- three body is
pretty much always relevant and it has
the opportunity to gain you even more
life which of course will trigger
various cards in this set as well. So I
think it's a B minus. Next up it's
solitary cell which for a red and white
is a rare artifact. When it enters you
exile target non-land permanent opponent
controls with mana value three or less
until this artifact leaves the
battlefield and you can pay one generic
and tap it and discard a legendary card
to draw a card. Hitting any nonland that
costs three or less is a nice deal for
two mana. You'll often be able to trade
up. This set also has a lot of
legendaries in it, too. Although there
aren't any at common that you would
really want to pitch, like on the
regular, like we saw in the Hobbit.
There are a decent number of them at
uncommon, and sometimes throwing one of
those away is better than casting it.
Although, I will say most of the time, I
think the legendaries in this set, if
you have the mana to cast them,
obviously you should cast them. So, this
might be useful for the more expensive
ones that you draw in the early game,
for example. So, pretty good removal
spell with a tiny bit of additional
upside. I'm giving it a B minus. Next
up, it's Stinger Quill Charm, which for
a black and a red is an uncommon
instant. It says, "Choose one.
Stingerquil charm deals three damage to
any target. Target creature gains first
strike and death touch intellive turn.
Create a two two colorless wizard
soldier creature token named cadet. It
gains haste intellive turn. So, I would
happily play this card if it was only
two of these modes, and I would pretty
happily play it if it was just the first
mode. So, the fact that this has three
modes, all of which are pretty
reasonable, seems pretty good to me. The
first mode obviously can kill creatures
and often trade up while doing it, but
it can also go after the opponent, which
this colored pair cares about. And of
course, if your opponent's at three or
less, it can just kill them. The second
mode is a good trick. When things line
up correctly, your creature will always
win that fight. And the last mode is
probably useful the least often, but you
can get this creature into play at
instant speed to block something.
Sometimes that's worth doing. Also,
sometimes just adding another body to
the board that can attack right away is
better than having either of the other
two things. So, this looks really good
to me. I'm giving it a B+. Next up, it's
Stingerquill Voxmancer, which for a
black and a red hybrid mana is a one-two
Goblin Soldier at uncommon. At the
beginning of upkeep, if it isn't
prepared, it becomes prepared. And its
prepare spell is vicious verse, which
costs a black red hybrid mana and deals
one damage to target opponent. This is a
really nice one drop. This coming down
on turn one means you're going to take a
lot of damage between its ability to
just attack in the early game and its
ability to ping every single turn from
then on. that can add up quickly and
gets even better with spell and damage
payoffs. And the fail case here is that
your opponent kills your one mana card
and probably for more than one mana.
There will be some games where it's too
slow and small to make a difference, but
I like this on the whole, giving it a B
minus. Next up, it's Stinging Vitriol,
which for a black and a red is a rare
sorcery that does two damage to target
opponent. That player reveals their
hand, you choose an onland card from it,
they discard that card. So, this is a
nice disruptive spell. And even if your
opponent's hand is empty, it gives you
some value in terms of damage. And as
we've seen, there are reasons for doing
that beyond just doing damage. And when
this does let you do two and take away
your opponent's best card, it'll feel
particularly good, but it's also true
that it's not a card that really adds to
the board. I'm giving it a C++. Next up,
it's Tam's Resistance, which for one
generic and a blue green hybrid man is a
common sorcery. Put a plus and plus one
counter up to one target creature gains
vigilance into turn. Empower Jace four.
So you can sort of add draw a card with
some upside to this because of empower
Jace and two mana to draw a card and put
a counter on something and give it
vigilance until end of turn is a pretty
solid card. It's often going to give you
an attack you didn't have before and
that is even more likely once you add
vigilance to the mix because you don't
have to worry as much on the back swing
if you're going to have an additional
creature untapped in the form of the one
you're attacking with. and it's cheap
enough that later in the game you can
draw into another card and double spell
too thanks to the Jace counters it gives
you. This looks pretty good to me on the
whole. Feels like it does a lot for two
mana. I'm starting it at a C++.
Next up it's Tenyard Tether Mage which
for one generic a red and a green is a
one-1 human artificer at rare. When it
enters you may sacrifice a land. If you
do create two tapped heartwood tokens
and you can tap two untapped artifacts
you control to put two plus one plus1
counters on this creature. It's
basically always going to be worth
sacrificing a land to get two heartwood
tokens. You end up netting a mana. And
the heartwood tokens in most ways are
better than lands because they help you
with your artifact payoffs like the
tenure tether mage itself. Plus, they
also produce two colors of mana unlike
most lands in this set. So, this will
ramp your mana and it has the capacity
to grow pretty quickly. You know, you're
going to have other heartwood tokens and
you're going to have other artifacts,
too. Red green has plenty of artifacts
running around to help grow this. Can
also grow it at instant speed. All of
that seems really appealing to me.
They're going to be sometimes where it's
awkward. You know, the Heartwood tokens
do intertapped. So, this may end up
being a three mana 1 one for a turn, and
that can end up being kind of bad for
you, but it will have already generated
value, so it's not even a disaster if
your opponent kills it for like one
mana. I'm giving this a B+. Next up,
it's Theix's Charm, which for a blue and
a black is an uncommon instant. Choose
one counter target on creature spell
unless its controller pays two generic.
Target creature gets minus two minus two
intentive turn. mill three cards, then
draw a card. The third one is always
going to be reasonably useful in your
blue black deck. It's going to put four
total cards in your graveyard cuz the
charm is going there, too. And that
sounds like it's going to be a really
good thing to do in this color pair. And
then you have these other two modes that
are more situationally good. You know,
sometimes killing a X2 with the second
mode is worthwhile. And if you have the
mana up and you can counter a good
non-creature spell and your opponent
can't pay the tax, then that feels
pretty good, too. I like that this one
does a lot with the synergy in the
particular color pair while also
offering two other modes that are good
in the right spot, giving it a B minus.
Next up, it's Theorix's Meta Mage, which
for two generic and a blue black hybrid
mana is a two three shade wizard at
common. It enters prepared and it has
threshold. It gets plus one plus hero
and has flying and it has that omit
variables spell which mills three cards.
The baseline here is very underwhelming,
but between its own omit variables and
the overall theme and two of the black
decks in this format, especially blue
black, this is going to turn into a
pretty real aerial threat in the mid to
late game, while of course also helping
set up all of your other graveyard
nonsense. I think this is a C. Next up,
it's Twined Vision, which for one
generic and a blue red hybrid mana is a
rare instant. Draw a card. If this spell
wasn't cast from your hand, draw two
cards instead. and it has flashback for
one generic and two blue red hybrid mana
and you discard a card. This is an
interesting think twice variant. It can
give you two spell triggers which blue
red cares about while digging you deeper
in your deck. And ultimately it does
give you a two for one. Being an instant
helps it out too as you can choose to
use it only when it makes the most
sense. Still it doesn't add to the board
and that's always a concern. I'm giving
it a C. Next up it's Twisted Fates which
for two generic two white into black is
an uncommon sorcery. Destroy target
nonland permanent. put a plus and plus
one counter on each creature target
player controls. This is pretty great.
Sure, a five mana sorcery is definitely
clunky, but this makes that cost well
worth it. You'll destroy your opponent's
best non-land while buffing your entire
board. That is going to endame
sometimes. You know, you take down their
best blocker, suddenly all of your
creatures are better attackers. That's a
hugely swingy play and it's just going
to happen with Twisted Fates, which is a
great removal spell thanks to the
counters that it'll put all over your
board. And it's not like it even feels
bad if you only have one or two
creatures. It's still going to feel
pretty good in that spot, just not, you
know, game-breaking. I'm giving it a B+.
Next up, it's Ulderos Theix, which for
three generic, a blue, and two black is
a five5 Elder Sphinx at mythic rare.
It's got flying, and when it enters, if
you cast him, exile up to one target
non-land card of each card type from
your graveyard. Copy those cards. You
may cast any number of spells with total
mana value six or less from among the
copies without paying their mana cost.
Yeah, this is nuts. The first time I
read it, I thought you could only cast
one spell with a mana value of six or
less, and I thought that would be an
amazing card. It would be a bomb already
if that's all it did. But it can do way
more than that. You can exile a couple
of three mana removal spells and cast
both of them, which in that case, you
get a full-on three for one. Sometimes
you'll be able to cast three things that
are worthwhile. It is true you need the
contents in your graveyard, but I think
as we've seen in this video and as we'll
see in the rest of the set review, Blue
Black is not going to have a problem
throwing cards in the graveyard and
having cards of different types in the
graveyard is just going to happen
naturally. Sure, having an instant and a
sorcery removal spell, maybe that's
asking things to line up a little bit
too well, but that's sort of like the
ideal case. Getting a creature and a
removal spell back is also great. There
are going to be times where someone
casts three or four spells with this.
There are going to be times where they
cast one big really powerful six mana
spell with it. There's just a lot that
this can do. And oh by the way, once the
dust settles from all the spells you
cast, you still have a five five flyer
around that is probably a massive threat
in the air. This is a huge bomb, giving
him an A+. Next up, it's Vigor Bloom
Charm, which costs a green and a white,
and it's an uncommon instant, and it
says, "Choose one target permanent you
control gains hex proof and
indestructible until end of turn. You
draw a card and gain three life or put a
plus and plus one counter in target
creature you controlled and it fights
target creature and opponent controls.
This is another really nice charm. The
third mode is the one that's going to be
the best the most often because it's
just a good removal spell. We've seen
two mana, put a counter on your guy, and
it fights something else be a good card
in the past, especially at instant
speed. And that's what this is. It's
going to be able to be a good removal
spell that also offers a permanent buff
to your creature. But then when you have
this in your hand, it's also a great way
to blink removal spells with the first
mode and occasionally win combat. The
second mode is honestly probably the one
you use the least here. And you'll only
use it when you either are really
desperate to draw into something else or
you have a bunch of life gain payoffs on
the board, which is certainly possible
in green white. On the whole, this just
looks really good. The modality is
awesome, and the first and third mode
are both really good in the right spot,
and the right spot for the third mode
isn't that hard to find. I'm giving it a
B+.
Next up, it's Vigorbloom Vanguard, which
for one generic and a green white hybrid
mana is a two two troll druid at
uncommon. and it enters prepared. Each
creature you control with a plus and
plus one counter on it has vigilance and
it has seed suture that green white
prepare spell. So if this was a three
mana 2 two that put a counter somewhere
and gain me a life, I'd play it in
basically all of my decks. And this is
just so much better since you can pay it
in parts if you want to. Putting the
counter on itself also means it's a
three mana 3 three with vigilance
because its own ability will buff it.
And the vigilance upside might also make
things better for other creatures you
already have in play. And the vanguard
can help make that happen by putting the
counter on something that can attack
immediately. And of course, you're
probably going to have more seed suture
around. One sort of interesting thing
about this card is that red white is
actually the plus and plus one counter
deck while green white is the life gain
deck, but it's going to overlap into
both of those decks really well because
it's just a good card on rate that also
happens to do things both of those decks
care about. This looks like a B to me.
Next up, it's Vindictive Triumph, which
for one white and two black mana is a
rare instant. Exile target creature or
planaineswalker. If that permanence mana
value was three or less, return it to
the battlefield tapped under your
control, exiled at the beginning of the
next instep. So, this is a good removal
spell for creatures or planaineswalkers.
Three mana to take one of those down
with exile is pretty nice. The other
part of the card will only matter with
like the exact right kind of thing that
you're exiling. Most of the time you're
going to want to exile something that
has a higher mana value anyway. But
sometimes you'll be able to kill a
creature that has an interest trigger.
So killing your opponent's creature and
then getting the interest trigger is
pretty good. Sometimes you'll want to
kill their creature and then bring their
thing back and then you can sacrifice
it. That is something Black White's
interested in doing. Most of the time
this is a good three mana removal spell
and every now and then you'll get some
additional upside. I'm giving it a B+.
Next up it's Warriors Blades which for
two generic, a red and a white is an
uncommon artifact equipment. When it
enters, it deals three damage to any
target and you gain three life. The
equip creature gets plus two plus one
and it is equipped cost for three, but
it costs one less to cast for each plus
one plus one counter on the creature it
targets. This is really good. It comes
down to remove something and gains you
life. If this didn't have the ability to
reduce its cost, it would still be a
really good card because it has a big
impact on the board. And then sure, it's
kind of a subpar equipment, but it
already did something. And now the fact
that it sits around offering a bonus is
just great additional upside. But this
gets even better because in red white
you're going to have counters around and
equipping this could be really easy. One
sort of awkward thing is sometimes you
want to equip something that doesn't
have counters. In fact, I'd say more
often than not you do want to equip
something that doesn't have counters so
that you have more creatures who can
attack into your opponent's creatures.
And so you're going to pay three for
this sometimes, even in the plus and
plus one counter deck. But like I just
said, even if it always costs three to
do that, it would be really good and
it's going to be cheaper sometimes. So,
I think this is a B.
Next up, it's Whiplash Wordsmith, which
for three generic and a black red hybrid
mana is a three- three vampire sorcerer
at common. It enters prepared, and as
long as an opponent was dealt non-combat
damage this turn, it has flying and
haste and it has vicious verse, that
black red prepare spell. You can kind of
look at this as a card with kicker. You
can do that with the ones that enter
prepared because if you have five total
mana when you play it, you can
immediately cast its prepare spell,
which will give it flying and haste
until end of turn. And if you have some
other ways to get non-combat damage
online before that, which is reasonably
likely in Black Red, you don't even need
the extra mana. Still, this thing has
hill giant stats, that's pretty abysmal.
It does have enough synergy stuff going
on that I think it'll make the cut in
your black red decks, but I don't really
think it's the payoff or enabler you're
really excited about. It's kind of a
mediocre way to do either of those
things. I think it's a C minus. Next up,
it's Woodwork Prodigy, which for two
generic and a red green hybrid man is a
three- three cat druid at uncommon. At
the beginning of your upkeep, if this
creature isn't prepared, it becomes
prepared and it has soul tether as its
prepared spell, that heartwood token
creating one. Spitting out mana rocks is
nice upside to have, especially when
you're in a color pair that can do lots
of extra stuff with heartwood tokens.
That's like what this color pair is
built to do. Use them to ramp, use them
for artifact payoffs, etc. So, I think
this is a B minus. All right. From here,
we're going to look at the multicolored
cards that are part of the echoed pairs
sheet. This isn't exactly a bonus sheet,
but it is a group of cards that show up
in packs differently than other cards,
much like doubleface cards when we've
seen those before. They did this because
they wanted every pack to have at least
one of these echoed pairs in it. So, you
were making a choice between, you know,
the two different multiveres. And to
make sure that happened, they had to put
three of these in every pack. So,
they're going to be there. There are a
bunch of them at various rarities. are
all uncommon or higher rarities. So,
let's take a look at those. We've got
Edgar, ancient bloodlord, which for a
black and a white is a two three
legendary vampire noble at uncommon.
Whenever another creature or
planaineswalker you control dies, you
gain a life and he can pay two generic
and sack another creature or
planaineswalker and put a plus one plus
one counter on Edgar and he gains menace
until end of turn. You know, when I was
doing this set review, I considered
looking at both of the cards that are
part of the echoed pairs, but they're
always different colors, and I didn't
think it made much sense in terms of
like the set review to do that. So,
we'll be seeing his other form later.
It's green. And that's true of most of
the others on this list, too, that you
won't see both of their pairs in this
particular video because they're not the
same color. It would have been kind of
cool for flavor reasons, but it doesn't
matter really for gameplay reasons.
Anyway, this has nice stats and it'll
gain you a bit of life if he remains in
play. His sacrifice ability costing two
is a little bit expensive, but it's also
pretty good since it turns Edgar into an
ever greater attacker. The fact you can
sacrifice your Jace tokens is appealing,
too. And the fact that just using the
loyalty abilities will eventually gain
you life from the Jace tokens, that
certainly matters as well. And the
format has enough other fodder around
for this ability to do its thing. And I
mean, the floor here is a two mana 2
three that's going to gain you some
life. and sometimes it's going to turn
into a very real threat. Think he's a B
minus. Next up, it's Hatra, the desert
fang, which for two generic, two black,
and a green is a three three legendary
human cleric at uncommon. When she
enters for each opponent, you put X -
one minus one counters and up to one
target creature that player controls,
where X is the greatest mana value among
cards in your graveyard. This will
typically come down and just kill
something straight up. It reminds me a
little bit of the black green signpost
from the Final Fantasy set. That card
did come with flying and this one
doesn't. But yeah, I'm always going to
be into a creature that adds to the
board while subtracting from my
opponents. And black green decks aren't
going to have a problem having a three
or four mana thing in the graveyard that
will allow you to kill your opponent's
thing. Sometimes you'll have something
really expensive in there and really be
able to kill anything. And hey, even if
you can't kill the thing, putting
counters on something is valuable, too.
I think this is a B. Next, it's K Gilded
Guardian. He has a hybrid mana cost
where you can pay one mana of each color
to cast him, but you can also pay two
generic for any of those manas of a
single color. In other words, if you
don't have white mana, but you have the
other four colors, you can pay six total
mana and still cast him. He's a
legendary artifact creature golem at
rare. He's got vigilance and trample.
And when he enters, you draw a card for
each color among other artifacts you
control. This doesn't feel very good for
limited. He's tough to cast even with
the hybrid option. And colored artifacts
aren't all over the place in this set.
The one place where it might work
sometimes is in red green because
heartwood tokens are red and green. So
he'll at least draw you two cards, but
you're still doing a ton of work to get
him out there. You're either paying too
much mana in terms of total mana you
spend or you're going to have to try
really hard to produce all five colors
of mana or some mix thereof. No matter
what, I don't feel like he's going to be
easy enough to cast or easy enough to
abuse to really be worth it in most
limited decks. Giving him a D. Next,
it's Kiora of Salt and Sand, who for one
generic, a green and a blue is a two-
four legendary Muroke noble at uncommon.
Whenever you attack, if you've activated
a loyalty ability this turn, untap
target attacking creature. It can't be
blocked this turn. And she also gives
Planaines walkers you control minus 8.
Create an 88 blue Leviathan creature
token with hexroof. Like we saw earlier,
Blue Green is really into making Jace
tokens. And this gives you two really
good reasons to be doing it. If you cast
her and you already have a Jason play
and you can use his minus one or
whatever, you suddenly have an
unblockable creature with pseudo
vigilance, which is pretty good. If you
don't already have a Jason play, she's a
little less impressive, but at least
she's a three mana 2 four. And once you
do have a Jason in play, she can start
doing a lot of work thanks to him using
his loyalty abilities. And if you're so
good at empowering Jace that your Jace
has like a ton of counters, well, he can
start slamming big creatures on the
board. Probably just one, but one's
enough for the most part. those Jesus
can't add to the board. Suddenly making
it so all of this loyalty you've built
up on him can make an 88 Leviathan is a
big deal. That said, it does feel a
little bad that she doesn't come with a
way to make one of those Jace tokens.
She'd probably be too good if she did
because then you'd always get that
trigger, assuming you have a creature
who can attack, you would get that
trigger right away. So even if she had
empower Jace one, maybe that would be
too good. And there's not really a
middle ground between that. I have a
feeling they probably tried that in
design and she was too good. And I could
definitely see that being the case, but
I feel like you really needing to have a
card somewhere else, say empower Jace,
for her to really get going does make
her into just a three mana two four
sometimes, and that's not amazing. I'm
giving her a C++, but I really hope
she's better. Next up, it's Mabel Valley
Hero, who for one generic a red and a
white is a one-two mouse soldier at
uncommon, a legendary one. And when she
or another creature you control enters,
put a plus one plus one counter on
target creature that entered this turn.
She counts herself. So, putting the
counter on her for the first trigger is
probably a good call because with two
toughness, she dies to a lot more
removal. After that, it's nice that
basically your creatures when they come
into play will enter with a plus and
plus one counter. This thing where it's
like on a creature that entered this
turn, like that is way worse than being
able to put the counter somewhere else
because sometimes what's great about
cards like this is that they make combat
on that same turn better. She can't do
that for the most part. A creature has
to have haste if that's the case. So,
she is somewhat limited in what she can
do in terms of in the immediate future
every time a creature enters, but
getting an extra counter on your
creatures that enter is also good. I do
worry about her small starting size. I
think she's a C++ overall. Next up, it's
Sahili, Jewel of Avishar, who for two
generic, a blue, and a red is a two four
legendary human artificer at uncommon.
She gives stoppers you control haste.
Whenever you cast an on creature spell,
you make a 1-1 colorless stoppter
artifact creature token with flying. I
wish she did something up front, but
anytime we've seen a whenever you cast a
non-creature spell trigger unlimited
that makes tokens, it's ended up being
an amazing card. Adding a one-1 thopter
with haste to every non-creature spell
is a serious bonus. But Sahili taking a
turn and the right card types to get
going on the next turn does keep her
from being like insane. I'm starting her
at a B minus. Next up, it's Tam the
possibility who for one generic, a
green, and a blue as a two for four
legendary Gorgon wizard at rare.
Planaineswalker spells you cast cost one
generic less to cast and you can pay one
man of each color and tap her and
proliferate X times. Rex has a number of
planaineswalker types among
planaineswalkers you control. So, she's
like the main character in the story and
she's going to be really cool in like
commander, but unfortunately she's not
especially good in limited. This set has
more planaineswalkers than normal, but
she doesn't actually help you very much
with the planaineswalker you're mostly
going to have, which is the Jace token.
You don't cast those, so you don't get
that discount. And paying one mana of
each color to proliferate once also not
very good. Sure, you'll do it if you
have her on the board. Getting another
loyalty on Jace isn't going to hurt, but
it's a lot of mana. You have to work
really hard to get it, and then it's a
very, very small payoff. So, she's
mostly a three mana two four without any
rules text in limited. I'm giving her a
D and she might just be worse.
Next up, it's Vasa, Soul of Stone, who
for a blue, a red, and a white is a
three- three legendary Gorgon wizard at
rare. Artifact creatures you control
have vigilance. And whenever you cast an
on creature spell, you make a 1-1
colorless sculpture treasure artifact
creature token with. Tap, sacrifice
token, add one mana of any color. She's
powerful, and those tokens can do a lot
of work. We just talked about how
non-creature spell triggers are just
really good. And there are enough other
random artifacts around for the
vigilance to matter, too. But I'm
skeptical this card's going to be worth
fullon going three colors for.
Especially because it's the sort of
thing you need to get down ASAP because
if you get your cards in the wrong
order, like you get her later, you can
finally cast her, but you've cast all
your non-creature spells cuz you didn't
have her third color mana, like that is
a real significant cost. And this format
does mostly feel like a twocolor format.
Sure, you might splash a third color,
but splashing a third color is always
going to make for somewhat inconsistent
mana for a card that you really want to
get down like on turn three before you
cast all your non-creature spells. So,
she has a really high ceiling. If you
can get her on the board at the right
time, she's amazing. It also gives you a
bunch of mana. Didn't even mention that,
but I'm concerned about her mana cost on
the whole and how it'll work out in this
limited format, giving her a C++. Next,
it's Vasa, the cutting glare. One of
only two of the Echoverse pairs that
we're actually going to see together in
this video. She costs two black and a
green for a 4-4 legendary Gorgon
assassin. At rare, she's got death
touch. And when she enters, if you
control six or more lands, you destroy
target permanent opponent controls, they
create a treasure token. So, a three
mana 44 with death touch is a really
nice floor. But obviously, if you can
help it, unless you're like really
curving out and killing your opponent,
you're probably going to want to wait
until she has her interest trigger
online because that removal effect is
really good. You do give your opponent
something back, but a treasure in
exchange for the best non-land permanent
at that stage of the game, especially is
great. I'd much rather give them that
than a creature token, for example,
unlimited. And it can even hit lands,
which isn't going to come up a lot, but
maybe it does. I think she's an A minus.
She'll generate a legitimate two for one
when you need them in the mid to late
game. And if you have to run her out on
three, it's not like she's terrible,
right? Let's move now to the artifacts
where we've got afterthought sentry,
which for two generic is a two two
artifact creature gargoyle at common.
You can pay two generic to give it
flying until end of turn. And when it
attacks, you exile up to one target card
from a graveyard. This is a very easy to
cast two mana 2 that has a couple of
little bits of upside and it's even an
artifact for decks that care about that.
You'll likely only start giving this
flying when you run out of plays, but
that's fine. And the graveyard hate
isn't irrelevant either. It's not a bad
two drop to run out there, but you
probably do hope you have something that
gets you started on a little more
assertive of a spot or helps more with
synergy. Giving it a C minus. Next up,
it's Archive Arbiter, which for six
generic is a 44 artifact creature sphinx
at uncommon. It's got flying and when it
enters, choose one. Destroy target
non-creature nonland permanent or you
gain four life. There going to be a lot
of occurrences where the first trigger
is irrelevant. You know, you can hit
enchantments and you can hit
non-creature artifacts and like a
planaineswalker token, a real
planaineswalker possibly, too, but
again, those are at mythic rare. You're
not going to see them all the time.
There aren't a lot of things it can hit
in this set. There are some things, but
I would say on average it's going to
enter and not have a target, so you have
to rely on it gaining you four life,
which isn't terrible. You add a somewhat
big body to the board with evasion and
gain four life. that can help you
stabilize, but it's not exactly a good
rate. On the flip side, when this does
have something to destroy, like an
oblivion ring type spell that gives you
back a creature, like that kind of thing
is going to feel amazing, but I think
this is just too expensive for what it
is most of the time to be a six- mana
card that you regularly want to put into
your deck. Giving it a C minus. Next up,
it's Cody Ravenous Codeex, which for
three generic is a one four legendary
artifact creature book construct at
rare. Whenever you cast a prepared
spell, copy it. You may choose new
targets for the copy, and you can pay
one mana of each color and tap it, and
each creature you control becomes
prepared. Only doing stuff with prepared
spells and creatures with prepare is way
too narrow. I mean, yes, they're in this
set. This video is really front-loaded
with prepare cards. Like, we're not
going to see nearly as much of them at
lower rarities in the other videos as we
saw in this one. And that helps you
understand that you're not going to see
them like everywhere in this set. So, a
lot of the time there's just not going
to be anything that Cody can do. It is
true that doubling a prepare spell is
pretty good. That's really the part of
Cody that matters the most. The five
mana part probably not really ever going
to matter. Being able to double prepare
spells is where you'll do really well.
You're going to get two tokens now and
so forth. So, there's potential here for
it to really go off, but I worry that
it's going to be hard to set that up
consistently. Like, I don't think Cody's
going to feel like an insane value
engine. I think it'll help you copy zero
to one prepared spells most of the time.
And when you're on that zero side, it's
going to feel pretty bad. But it does
have a pretty sweet ceiling, and I think
you would end up playing it in any deck
that has like two or more cards with
prepare spells just cuz the upside is so
high. But I think it's probably just a C
plus. Next up, it's the Echoverse
Fulcrum, which for two generic is a
mythic rare legendary artifact. When it
enters, you draw a card and then discard
a card. You can pay five generic, tap
it, and exile it to destroy all
creatures. Activate only as a sorcery.
So, this is a sweeper that ultimately
costs seven, and that's not usually very
good and limited. Sure, if you get
there, it can help you out if you're the
one who's behind, but relying on that is
tough. And yeah, it's true you can run
this out earlier since it's only two
mana, but if you do that, your opponent
knows it's coming and can adjust their
game accordingly. I do like that it
loots when it enters. It makes it more
likely that you have a decent follow-up
play on the next turn, but your opponent
still gets the chance to rebuild their
board before you ever do, as they do
with a lot of symmetrical sorcery speed
sweepers. So, I think this is clunky and
a little bit awkward, even though it
does have a powerful effect, giving it a
C++. Next up, it's Eye of Jace, which
for one generic mana is an uncommon
artifact. At the beginning of your
upkeep, surveil one. Then, if there are
seven or more cards in your graveyard,
sacrifice this artifact. It deals two
damage to each opponent and you gain two
life. This is an interesting card. Is a
oneman artifact that surveills one
during your upkeep really worthwhile? In
most sets, I think I would say it isn't.
Even if I do like getting some card
selection and graveyard action going
ASAP, I end up using up a card that
doesn't actually add to the board in any
way, shape, or form. So, but in this
set, you're going to be in decks
sometimes where getting a surveile
trigger regularly is going to be good
because you'll get a lot of extra value
out of it in addition to just the
graveyard and card selection value
surveil inherently has. And then
eventually, this does do two to your
opponent and you gain two. One thing I
wish though is that you had the option
to not do that because if your board has
a couple of surveil payoffs on it, you
would much rather just keep surveilling
every turn, but it's not a m trigger.
After you surveil, there are seven or
more cards. It just does the thing and
you don't have a choice. I think there
will be surveile decks that end up
running this, you know, blue white decks
in the format that end up running it,
but I think most of the time it's not
really going to be worth running. You
need to have gotten there in a big way
on surveiled payoffs to make it work.
Giving it a C minus. Next up, it's
Keeper of the Quiet Hour, which for
three generic is a 3-2 artifact creature
chimera at common. And when it enters,
you empower Jace, too. This stat line
almost always weighs a creature down in
a big way, but having an interest
trigger can certainly help a creature
overcome that problem. And this one will
at a minimum because it basically says
surveil one. Not an incredible trigger,
but there's also a chance you get your
Jace to the point where it can draw you
a card, like if it already had one
loyalty counter. That'll make it feel a
lot better. sort of make it feel like a
three mana 3-2 that draws you a card
when it enters, which is excellent.
Still, it's probably just a card that
only makes the cut when you don't have
something better or where you really
need more empower Jace or you need
another artifact. A three mana 32 really
is that bad in this day and age that you
need to do a lot to overcome it, like
you know, draw a card when it enters,
but certainly it doesn't do that
consistently enough. I think this is
just a D+. Next up, it's living library,
which for two generic is a 04 artifact
creature book illusion at common. You
can pay six and sacrifice it and truce
target creature or planaineswalker. An
opponent controls its owner shuffles it
into their library. This is better than
the usual cheap artifact with a super
efficient removal mode. And that's
because it does actually add to the
board before it does the removal thing,
but it's not like a 04 is all that
meaningful. Your opponent can attack
into it without worrying at all. So, it
just ends up preventing a bit of damage
until it turns into a bad removal spell.
I think it's just a D. Next up, it's
Medic's Kite Sale, which for two generic
is a common artifact equipment. The
equip creature gets plus one plus hero
and has flying. And whenever this
creature attacks, you gain a life, and
the equip cost is two generic. This is
going to feel clunky to cast and equip,
but it does have the ability to turn any
creature into an aerial threat. And if
you're interested in gaining life, that
sounds even more appealing. This will be
worthwhile in some decks for sure, but I
don't think you run this card with
regularity, giving it a C minus. Next
up, it's Murmuring Volume, which for
three generic is a common artifact book.
You can tap it for one mana of any
color. You can pay two generic, tap it,
and discard a card to draw a card. There
are only a few three mana mana rocks
that have actually been quality cards
and limited. And I don't think this one
really gets there. It doesn't add to the
board. And while its ability does become
relevant, especially in the late game,
this is going to feel like a liability a
lot of the time since it does so little
apart from producing mana, the value of
which tends to decline throughout the
game. And it's not like it's that good
early either since you need to be
curving out with bodies most of the time
and playing a three mana card that
doesn't add to the board is a pretty big
liability. I think it's a D.
Next it's K Argent defender. So here is
the other one of the echoed pairs that's
actually in this video. He's too generic
for a one- three. He's a legendary
artifact creature golem at rare and
artifacts and creatures entering the
battlefield don't cause abilities to
trigger. So keep in mind this is
symmetrical. In other words, it'll shut
down your interest triggers, too. And
that makes him a lot less appealing
because in this day and age, it's hard
to know whether your deck or your
opponents has more of that kind of
trigger, especially in limited. In other
formats, you can find ways to break the
symmetry by playing cards that have
interest triggers that are downsides.
But we're talking about limited here.
You can't expect to consistently be able
to do that at all. He's mostly just a
two mana 1 three, and that's not very
good. He's a D. There's also Traxxo
Scourge Eternal who for four generic is
a five- four legendary artifact creature
dragon constructed uncommon. It's got
trample and it doesn't untap during your
untap step. Whenever you cast an
artifact and creature spell, you untap
Traxxos. I wish this untapped when you
had an artifact enter. That way the
heartwood tokens would untap this. But
as is, it's limited to actual artifact
and creature spells. Basically, this is
a four mana 54 with trample that has a
pretty real downside. and a four mana 54
with trample and no downside at all is
probably a C plus at best. It is true
that you can sometimes turn this sort of
thing into upside like by giving this
pseudo vigilance. You know, you can
attack with him and then play an
artifact or creature spell in your
second main phase and untap him. But I
think it'll be more of a downside than
an upside. I'm giving him a C minus. All
right, let's move to the lands now.
First, there are a cycle of five rare
dual lands, all of which entertapped
unless you control two or more other
lands. As usual, the sets rare dual land
offers really good fixing. These will
even enter untapped for most of the
game. I'm giving them a C+. Next,
there's Hall of Echo, which is a rare
land they can tap for colorless, and you
can pay five, and it becomes a copy of
target creature you control until end of
turn. The legend rule doesn't apply to
permanence you control this turn. This
is a utility land that I think is
actually worth running. You know, a lot
of the times a land that can only tap
for colorless and then has some random
activated ability just isn't worth it
and limited because it makes a huge dent
in the consistency of your mana base if
one of your 17 lands can't produce
colored mana. Getting them early like as
one of two lands in your opening hand
feels completely miserable. And this has
those problems. But sometimes they come
with an ability that actually makes it
worth making your mana a little bit
worse. And I think this one does. The
fact that it can turn into one of your
creatures. I mean, it's basically a
really flexible creature land. One that
even doesn't care about the legend rule,
which is good cuz this set has a lot of
legendaries. Sure, five mana is a lot,
but there are a lot of board states
where making a copy of your best
creature for five mana is just really
good. Your opponent has to account for
this land before they attack on their
turn, too. Like, there's just a lot
going on with this card that I like. But
the hit it takes to your mana base does
keep it from being like incredible. I
think it's just a C++, but there are
going to be games where this thing can
take over. You just have to be ready for
the games where it also hurts your mana.
Next, there's Theorist Sanctum, which is
a rare land island. As it enters, you
can behold a Jace, and if you don't, it
enters tapped. Remember, that means you
can show your opponent a Jace in your
hand or point to a Jace you have in
play, which in this case, of course,
mostly means the empower Jace. And
speaking of empower Jace, you can pay
two generic and a blue and tap it to
empower Jace, too. This liner untapped a
reasonable amount of the time,
especially in the mid to late game, and
having it tapped like on turn one
normally isn't a huge problem. And this
activated ability is a good place to
sink mana in the late game, and can
certainly help you find a way to win
with all that sweet Jace value. Giving
this a C++. Next, there's Hex Haven
Dueling Arena, which is an uncommon land
that can tap for colorless. You can pay
two generic and tap it, and target
creature that attacked this turn becomes
prepared. Activate only as a sorcery.
any for generic and tap it and target
creature becomes prepared. So there was
a prepare land in secrets of stricks
haven and the hex haven version probably
isn't any better. Sure, it can prepare
something a little bit more efficiently
if the creature has attacked, but you're
playing a land that doesn't produce
colored mana. You know, talked about how
big of a downside that is earlier. So
having an ability that only matters in
corner cases isn't going to be worth it.
I think it's an F. There is also a cycle
of common dual lands and intertapped
unless you control a planaineswalker
like vigorloom annex here which can tap
for green or white. They'll actually
enter untapped sometimes thanks to
empower Jace like especially if you're
in the blue green color pair. I think
you can count on these being untapped
more often than in other color pairs but
empower Jace is all over the set. So
you're going to have it in or untapped.
And you know when we have these dual
lands that always intertapped they're
still pretty good because of the fixing
they offer. And these have the upside of
not always doing that. I think they are
a C++. I think they're probably a little
worse than the rare cycle is. Next,
there's room of refuge, which is a
common land that enters tapped, and as
it enters, you choose a color. You can
tap it to add one mana of the chosen
color. You can also pay five and tap it
and sacrifice it to put two plus and
plus one counters on target creature.
Activate only as a sorcery. This can
kind of fix your mana, though. Keep in
mind, this kind of card is always
awkward when you're trying to splash a
color because you really don't want to
name your splash color with this if you
get it in your opening hand, for
example. That's just really awkward. And
so using up one of your sources of
fixing that way kind of makes it harder
to count this as fixing exactly. It can
do it, of course. If you get it later
and you have the card in your hand that
you're splashing, obviously then you are
going to name that color, but it can be
awkward. And I think that's important to
note, as is entering tapped 100% of the
time. That last additional mode is
pretty nice to have when you don't have
anything else to do. It can certainly
make your creatures better at the right
time. I think this one's a C. There is
also a land on the special guest sheet,
which is just 10 cards that are super
rare. There's no bonus sheet, per se, in
this set. The bonus sheet is instead
basically those mirrored pairs, but they
show up a lot more than a normal bonus
sheet. They're just sort of a unique
sheet as opposed to a bonus one. But
there are special guests. They're
exceedingly rare. I decided this time
around I'm just going to look at all of
them in their respective videos because
there's only 10 of them and one of them
does qualify for this multiolor and
colorless videos. That is Eye of Ugan,
which is a legendary land. Makes your
colorless Hdrazi spells cost two generic
less to cast. You can pay seven generic
and tap it and search up a colorless
creature card, reveal it, put into your
hand, and then shuffle. I already told
you how I feel about lands that don't
produce colored mana. How about a land
that doesn't produce any mana? Yeah,
this is terrible and limited. There's
one Eldrazi in this set. The tutor
ability does have a few more cards that
it can grab beyond Emerool, but you
don't want to play a land that is
basically just a seven mana tutor to
grab some mediocre six- mana 44 Flying
Sphinx. It's just a huge liability to
use up a land drop on a card like this
that mostly doesn't do anything. It's an
F. All right, so those are all the
multicolored and colorless cards in
Reality Fracture. In the next video,
I'll look at all the white ones. If you
enjoyed this video, don't forget to like
it and share it so that others can enjoy
it, too. If you want to make sure you
catch future videos like the rest of
this set review, don't forget to
subscribe. And if you're watching this
video after more set review videos have
come out, you should see a playlist on
your screen shortly. Thanks for
watching.